foreign
it's about how to
self-reliant when there are many Doma teachers
when there are many Doma teachers
all claiming essentially their own
uh
technique View
process what is the way that one can become
what is the way that one can become
self-reliant before Right View
laughs no self-reliance starts with a review
no self-reliance starts with a review
that's the that's the Peril of
photogenous situation yeah
so um
yeah that's why you have to be extra
careful and uh
and uh
extra careful extra honest
extra transparent
so you're not you're not acting out of
mere preferences
um but actually like sound reasoning
um using your intelligence to discern
and knowing that for as long as you are
not self-reliant
well you should not entirely
rely on somebody else and take for
granted but everything has to be
investigated in other words
um
with the goal of developing that
self-reliance yeah yeah
obviously
all of this needs to be done on the
basis of keeping the presets since
restraint
and so how many so-called Dharma
teachers actually have two self-reliance
as a goal in their teaching
because if that's not the goal yeah
that's exactly yeah
yeah one of the criteria you can start
seeing then where does this teaching
lead
another question yeah go ahead
so
in the gradual training all the way up
to Jana
um the journal would be the right
meditation just so
just so
in that gradual training it doesn't
exactly Express
he achieves Right View so in the gradual
training it brings about Janna but
it doesn't explicitly mention Right View
but right view is a prerequisite for
John as I understand yeah usually the
gradual gradual training is is told to
the monks they are the ones that
undertook the training
so generally unless it's it's other way
around when Buddha is talking to the
monks unless it's clearly stated that
the monk does not have the right view
they would have the right vehicle so all
bikers and because there's because you
should contemplate this it's already
presupposed that they understood what
the practice is otherwise the Buddha
wouldn't be talking on the level as if
they already know what the practice is
and then encouraging them further
so there were instances when when some
of the bigquies were not didn't even
have the right View and those suitors
they would have clearly states it and
then they would usually at the end of
that's what they get the right View and
so on
um so
um
having said that you don't have
technically you don't have to have the
right view to have John and you just
need to be fairly withdrawn mine grind
up from sensuality
um so but again any
any instruction any notion any
contemplation that you might do that
would result in that today is known on
account of the Dharma and the sooties so
to be highly unlikely that you would be
able to free your mind from sensuality
overcome it in Jannah and not understand
other much kind of lower aspects of the
from the suitors such as you know four
noble truths and so on so it would be it
would be unlikely that you wouldn't get
the right view but say even again
theoretically you still don't get the
right View
if you have developed genres means your
mind would have already been pure from
all those pollutions
um I don't know 95 let's say which means
it will be much more likely much easier
to then get their idea because there are
less abstractions of her obscuring it
that's the difference when the Buddha
would say some person has a lot of dust
in their eyes some person doesn't in
other words some some some person's mind
is much more developed
um someone else's isn't and they would
need much like instruction repeated and
so on and would take a lot a lot longer
for them to uh to get the right view but
if the mind is developed from the things
that are obscuring this understanding
then if you turn it directly towards the
understanding it won't take that much
because as I said there's not much
standing in the way
so you don't need to wait to have the
right view before starting a gradual
training yes yeah yeah that's you know
but by doing it you you actually have a
chance to understand it for what it is
and by doing together I do uh
but as long as that doesn't mean that
people should be doing a technique that
they think is the gradual training they
will then bring the pleasure of Janna
they will then result in the Right View
because that's seriously wrong with you
so uh in the process of doing the
gradual training you need to be
approaching your wrong views about where
the practice is
the place of sensory strength and
withdrawal that self-transparency so
and that's what I'm saying like like if
you start keeping the precepts rightly
not relying on
the authority of a teacher not relying
even on a community in that sense or a
tradition but doing it internally
as as yours as solely dependent on your
determination uh your upholding of that
direction it will be highly unlikely that you
it will be highly unlikely that you
would remain non-transparent about your
motives and expectations and and other
kind of
views you might have
but usually as I said when people start
their graduate training they would take
on the precepts on account of one of
these factors so that they don't have to
think for themselves or they don't have
to doubt it they don't have to second
guess it every day it's like no you do
have to that's kind of the point that's
how you realize the extent of the
hindrances of the doubt of the mind and
so on
um so understanding how to do the
gradual training rightly see that's
always something that
can be developed in people like it's not
just you read these steps and do them
because each and one of those steps
their layers you can peel off of until
you do it rightly in the beginning it
won't be it won't be correct for sure
but so yeah it doesn't mean you
shouldn't try anything until you get the
right View
but you need to recognize that whatever
you try without the Right View well it
won't be light for that reason
practicing like restraint just in
regards to
uh non-activity per se me not trying to
do anything
uh particularly of any hindrance that
might happen uh
I get maybe a point where
it feels like any investigation I do is
out of the desire to get rid of the
doubt about it so it just feels more
pleasant to not think about it well yeah
so as I said it's not it's not like
something you can just stick to one
just stick to one way so never never act
out never do this because again it
depends on why you're doing it at a time
so if it's too tight you need to loosen
it it's too loose you need to tighten it
so if you are actually preferring the
pleasure of non-investigation that's
probably a good sign that you should
start investigating
yeah and even if my mind though is coming out
and even if my mind though is coming out
of the desire it doesn't matter it's not
because otherwise it would be pleasant
yeah so you realize desire is where the
so you realize desire is where the
pleasure is yeah
perhaps another factor in questioning
the authenticity of the teacher or
teaching is
to find out how prepared the teacher is
to having discussions
because some of them say no this is my
practice this is my method it's working
for me and and based on that they
basically block everything else
but if there is no attitude to even be
open to Alternative views
um or to give reasons and Arguments for
what they think what they doing is right
yeah that's the yeah then that people
might be open to views but no no can you
actually reason your position give
arguments not just like I'm not hearing
any of this this is the way I did it
that's it Finnish story yeah so like can
can you ask questions can you get the
corresponding answer to what you asked
you know if like a generic whatever you
asked you just get well watching
Australia's Mantra or let go every
Everything Everything whoever comes
whichever life is just the same thing
just let go just just yeah just chance
just just sit across like that's again
if if they were the way out well surely
we would have come across it in the
suitors as as a way out but it was like
quite much more elaborate much more
layered as I said before
so
um that is that is definitely actually a
factor you can you can see even on the
basis of um of someone else's
instruction by register any closed kind
of faith-based just do this
or there is there is some
intellect behind it so to speak there is
some reason in there clear clear kind of
reflection that can then be you know
shared questioned uh and so on explain
differently and and and so on yeah
yeah it's that's definitely important
actually
in the soothers you know
whoever will come to the Buddha with the
question sometimes even quite
antagonistic on him to the base
it would never would always be able to
answer every question yeah it was you
know it doesn't matter who from what
direction let me apart those questions
he refused to answer but obviously then
he would give reasons for refusing to
answer those questions
it's like the ones they were based on
Instagram
also the seclusion is affected there's
this discourage where somebody
supposedly and says well we have all
these different wonders and have all
these views how can we now know which
one's right and then he does say okay
one factor is do these people actually
practically and divide the in seclusion
and and not just hang out with other
people the whole time that's now another
thing so that's basically even
regardless of this might be sort of
lesser standard but still right because
of that factor is not there it's very
questionable whether there's sufficient
strength in the minds to have the right
kind of discernments so yeah so that's
another Factor
I'd say maybe it's another Factor thing
to be aware of in this
things that it's not
um
it's not necessarily just about like
choosing a particular teacher even say
oh yeah no that's the one that I've
settled on and I'm pretty sure that
that's um because that would be obviously
um because that would be obviously
making yourself dependent on this I
think you need to kind of keep in mind
that the only
um way really that you'll have a
criteria to know which teacher
if there even is one for example like
you don't even need to take for granted
that there is even one teacher out there
who's teaching the same thing what you
what needs to be the priorities that you
yourself know what's right and what's
wrong for yourself and then from that
perspective you would be able to
be sure okay this this teaching I'm sure
because I've really trained in it and
I've verified it for myself that I can see
verified it for myself that I can see
what about if somebody can't help
they just can't help but but this is my
teacher I'm so inspired what do they do
do they go and find another one or what
do they do how do they deal with that
because everything that this person says
he's the right he's the right teacher
and and that's it but again
you don't know that so what do you do in
that occasion what how can you how can
you know whether your inspiration is
writing or wrong I mean your factual
Inspire your factory uplifting you
factually find sense it was being said
you just stop caring about anybody else
any other instruction
but how do you now not blind yourself
with that what do you do
take the medicine of the doctor yes and
yeah take your own faith you have to
actually apply it apply it to me and yeah yeah
apply it apply it to me and yeah yeah
okay the application but yeah that's do
you have something else good
and recognize this Blind Faith I mean as
a hindrance well and yeah maybe not as a
hindrance but recognize it as a factor
there and then question that like so
you'd like to deny it or I must find
another one or I must undo the
inspiration but it's like what is it
that I'm finding inspired is it
something a genuine inspiring or is just
the character of this person you know
the way he speaks the way he moves the
way he acts then I just find yeah that's
the right guy or something but or is it
no no factually on the basis of my
previous practice and everything else
things that are said that's what you
find inspiring things that you're
required to do as a practice that's what
you find inspiring and so on yeah okay
so I was if it's if it's that
as in if it's genuinely things that have
made you understood things that you
didn't hear from anybody else and that
um had actually made you see things in a
different way not just like oh this
clicks with what I was already thinking
sort of thing
um
then yeah that's a kind of a fairly good
criteria but even then I would say that
it's still not okay
but it's like so you might have
inspiration and then you start
questioning that as to what is the basis
for it what's your motivation behind
um see if you're afraid to question
uh what that teacher says not
necessarily with him if he's in the
other side of the world but with
yourself so it's like okay you know I got it now
so it's like okay you know I got it now
I understand what he's saying it's like
this is that this or this and then you
come across the opposing view oh is
there a passionate reaction to that is
there an upset is there a defense
mechanism in which case again that still
does not necessarily mean you're wrong
but you need to recognize it but why so
if if
there is a threatening view the only
reason I would be afraid or feel
defensive is because I'm not entirely
certain in what I think I understood
so then you use that
um that experience pretty much their
occasion to okay so then I need to
recognize that
I need to understand more of this
um or I need to or if there is no more
in that teaching then it is well I need
to then find a teaching that uh will be
impervious to doubt and even if I come
across the opposing views and so on they
will not be able to sort of immediately
switch them into that mode of oh I must
defend this or I'll just turn a blind
eye on think about it so intentionally
uh sometimes intentionally you will have
to bring up the doubt in regard to what
you think you understood
and then feel the weight of it and then
yeah see if it what you understood
remains there like uh of course at the
same time you you know when I say bring
up the doubt it doesn't mean like just
start spinning out of control and kind
of doubt but bring it up and leave it
there and then see what understanding
you have and uh
what what aspects of it are you doubting
is it irrational just pressured out or
there genuinely things that lack in
Clarity in which case that Clarity needs
to be developed
yeah and when there are no more things
that I can Clarity you just realize
you're just going around repeating the
same stuff
or otherwise answering the same things
to the questions your own doubt is
asking then you recognize okay now this
is just the hindrance of Doubt just sort
of acting for its own sake so then you
you stop until the Mind comes down but
then you can bring it up again if you're
too calm or find pleasure too much
pleasure then not provoking these uh
Reflections then you should do it in
that sense yeah
just to see if the the the the solid
understanding of it is there and whether
it would stand the test or not
but um a lot of our discussion so far
has um been based on this premise that
um been based on this premise that
the emphasis is on understanding which
isn't necessarily the case for
I think a lot of
interpretations of the Buddhist teaching
were I mean all right right sure yeah well
I mean all right right sure yeah well
yeah that's as we said in the beginning
that will easily
there will be a criteria they will
easily sort of
remove a lot of things that are presented as a
a lot of things that are presented as a
Buddhist teaching
because again if they don't bring
understanding and the clarity in regard
to the nature of suffering nature of
tangha the escape and so on
if if if if they teach you that if they
teach us things as some sort of
experience they will just occur to you
on account of certain practices you can
pretty much safely dismiss that in the
beginning right away that's just
difficult to see I think I mean yeah
based on yeah the dominance of I mean
most Buddhism today yeah so that's we
come back to that there is transparency
and so on if you just whatever you
found appealing whatever you're doing
whatever your practice is don't forget
about your own motivation in regard to
it and start questioning it
like why and does it add up and start
learning the soothers
and when I say learning I mean
investigate the meaning not just sort of
memorize the Pali and his
historiological context of of the texts
and stuff like that you know the actual
try to understand what's meant by those
things said two and a half thousand
years ago what do they refer to Here and
Now in this experience while I'm reading
the sutras those are the general
categories of the human mind of of the
five aggregates
so they are there while you're reading
about them but you're not seeing them so
you have to be take uh understand that
immediate level
yeah yeah that's one reason why it's
quite different I mean it is difficult
to start that process because
the searches are very when you first
come to them abstract and kind of weird
like why is this emphasis why is he
putting emphasis on this and this and
yeah that investigation obviously then
can lead you into then an understanding
of why emphasis is on the body or you
know or you know or conceiving or what
does that mean yeah
but also again in my experience now um
one one thing that's sort of uh almost
always overlooked is their
whom the suit is applied to
do I even meet the prerequisites of a
salmon and I don't mean like am I
formally ordained or something but am I
living withdrawn keeping the preset
secluded to what extent
uh because that is kind of the as I said
the basic threshold would the teacher
instruct um and uh yeah sure you had cases of
um and uh yeah sure you had cases of
householders
uh becoming sotopanos and so on upon
talking to the Buddha but good luck with
that now yeah it was a different time
but even then it was the same procedure
so to speak he would first glide into my
eye turn it away from sensuality and
household worries
then when that mind is blatant and sort
of uh Khan he wouldn't talk about the
Petals of centrality because he just
talks about patterns of centrality right
away on a mind it's not even Glidden or
on a mind it's not even Glidden or
composed to any extent well that's not
going to be taken lightly
uh so then you're glad in the mind
then he would teach about the Palace of
sensuality and the value of escape and
then they would understand it
and show them I then choose to go back
to their kind of household duties if
they have children and family and so on
but it's not something they cannot not
forget you can say they were lucky in a
way they were but even then it was not
some magical shortcut it was still the
same thing
so now you don't have to do this so
first you need to again Glide in the
mind and withdraw your mind from
household worries
then you have to start seeing the battle
and contemplating
invoking the Peril of sensuality so that
the Mind turns away
and then creating an affordable truth
won't be that far away
but most people's attitude is just
replace one thing with the other
and not really not really undo and then
build up on top of that undoing by
undoing more and more and more
and that's really the problem
might be worth
pointing out as well that isn't
a household average householders life
yeah it's very different it's not equal
to the average household in his life the
x is the centrality Comfort I mean I bet
Kings back then did not live as as
comfortably and luxuriously as people
today live generally which means when
you pick up suit your reading suited
with that sensuality meaning from a
completely wrong place and you're not
even aware that doesn't none of it so
again you can start learning sure and
then start undoing peeling off these
layers as I said but if you just ignore
that whole situation you are in your own
situation and then just go straight into
yeah and conceiving the molopolya is
it's like it's just going to be an
abstract Theory which is exactly how it
happens you have phds in Buddhism fluent
in Bali and not even being able to keep
the five presets
professors and people like that and it's
like it's just not done
even if it's just the the part you speak
it's not the download
and even if technically somebody one in
thousand people can become a sotopana
with very little sense restraint and so
on because they have so many other
faculties develop sure but that's not
the standard that was not standard back
then and it's not standard today
yeah celibacy is not the opposite of a
household life possible to be a
household on their service exactly
that's the easy mistake that that is
made I've noticed nowadays yeah well it
always it always goes in the kind of um
monks have to be celibate
so but I can't be a monk because of some
practical reasons I have a mother to
support her family thus I don't have to
be celibate yes that's that's the reason
in there yeah but it is still at the
same time means because I can't be a
monk that's I don't have to be
celebrated but I can still practice the
Dharma yeah that's a bit of a mix-up
idea yeah
yeah so like again a person can just if
you think like I don't
I can't be a monk but then at the same
time being celebrated or keeping the eight
being celebrated or keeping the eight
preset something like that well
um that's not necessary you know you can
practice Drama by keeping the five
precepts just ask yourself what do you
have to lose if you keep your presence
would that obscure didn't have a
practice or would that enhance it
what do you have to lose
and when I say please if that really
remains yeah
yeah
the extent of Engagement with centrality
is like
the other ones whether you eat at 12 45
or 9 30 it's pointless it's not it's
just don't don't overdo it don't indulge
it same sleeping as high luxurious
places means how you spend your days
You're Just in this luxury and comfort
to sleep in all the time lazy stretching
around like a wild board after the meal
is it what it says in the suitors
or is it a simpler life whereby you
don't overly indulge in sleep you don't
over indulge in food
and you said a bit
that's the eight precepts
you're not beautifying yourself for the
sake of it but if you stink after work
yeah put some deodorant on if you have
to go among other people you're not
doing it for the wrong reasons you're
not doing it for beautification or
attraction you're just doing it so
people don't complain and harass you
um have a shower and so on so the point
is it all boils down to that the the the
third precepts in the level of
withdrawal from Central desires sexual
desires in particular
so when when a precepts means basically
celibate that's the emphasis there [Music]
[Music]
I thought about before in terms of that
difference between the five precepts and
the eight precepts
just that it's not about yeah like she
said it's not about the specific
specificity of the presets with the five
precepts are more like
things that are just always on wholesome
and like it would be good for everybody
to keep them whether they want to
practice or not whereas eight Priestess
is more on the level of just okay what's
the kind of relatively bare minimum type
of lifestyle that kind of can set up
around myself context for that's
suitable for being watchful of my
intentions being moderate in in amazing
being wakeful being you know having
putting all that effort in so like okay
I need to live simply I need to just
you know eat for the right reasons can
help to sometimes limit the time
you know not and just entertain myself
with distractions
and obviously Services it's like yeah
like the food places I mean the the
monks used to some of the monks we've
got peanut butter at night
in the beginning there was no
there was no stipulation there then
there were lots of practical issues
arising with that you know
attacked by wild animals robbers scaring
scaring people and so on so then they
would say I'll just do it between like
the dawn
and the noon do it at the right time
where kind of things require people
around it's daylight it's just safer
but then even then uh some monks would
would not eat just one meal a day they
would eat during that period of time
they would eat you know two or whatever
then they would encourage them to eat
one meal a day as he does but he never
made that into it all either
um so it's again it's just if you if you
have the right context you can see the
the nature the purpose of the of the
fireplace it's already preset and then
not fall into these technicalities oh
well see technically it's fine not hey
that again it's like where's your
where's your intention behind all of
that crazy motivation and when you when
you start getting the right context you
usually give keep the five precepts with
celibacy why not do that like sure maybe
why not do that like sure maybe
the merely serve at your work at 4 30
whatever in the evening you can that's
fine don't eat anything before it is
there and that's it
um so you don't have to technically then
follow these these guidelines but just
keep the five precepts which as we said
before it's the basic wholesome behavior
and then add celibacy to it for the
third base set so I think that for many
people there will be
certainly enough to start in the right
direction they're developing
transparency and so on but uh if you can
keep the the celibacy precepts you won't
have a problem with not sleeping on a
highway should you sleeping place or
eating one meal a day or something like
that none of that would be an issue
perfumes well who cares about it now
yeah because it's really it all boils
down to them and that's the that's the
main the main the main strength the main
pull the main issue the main obstacle
foreign
the pressure of sexuality
in this type of environment we're in
other Monastery environments I've been
to the it seems like just the reduction
in the sort of
stimulus of what's happening around you
like reduces it like so much yeah of course
reduces it like so much yeah of course
and then as soon as I go back yeah
everything is like it's like pressuring
it's like it felt like maybe for a
certain extent of time that that
defilement had been like very
easily been pushed away right but then
as soon as I'm back in the city
environment then I'm walking in the
street and I'm keeping my eyes downcast
and everything is you know pressuring me
it's like as if I've lost progress so to
say so where is the where is the
development is is it to
seclude yourself until essentially
you're an anagami emergency well the
development is um
like in how
how far you would act out yeah
and if you're not acting out development
will be on the level of how pressured
you are because that that pressure would
lessen uh with the with the time with the
uh with the with the time with the
Android understanding with with the
contemplation of
when you're not pressured with truly
understanding the pedal of centrality as
we spoke before debate the
dissatisfaction and and really cementing
those contexts and their perspective
uh but uh
yeah the unsuitable environment will
still bombard your senses and that will
always be a form of harassment now
foreign that harassment of his senses is not
that harassment of his senses is not
something that he can sort of act out of
it's just inconceivable
because the panel debate has been
completely shunned and stood correctly
abandoned but they still feel the
harassment their eyes are still harassed
with with the perception they want to
pervert itself so to speak the ugly
wants you to see it as beautiful and so
on there was that there are the power
supply where you know he was already if
not fully enlightened he was already Way
Beyond centrality and he went home and
the father tried to entice him first
with the wealth got his wives to to try
and seduce him and he says stop
harassing me like all this is harassment
so it's not that he was like oblivious
to what was happening the significance
of those acts of seductive behavior of
the value of gold and so on but he could
not not see it for what it is
um so he's all father off told him to
better to put a gold at the bottom of
the river
because it would bring less suffering
their way and called his wife's sisters
and they kind of got a bit upset and
painted or something
uh but yeah he was actually like when I
say annoyed in the terms of angry but
yeah his senses were being bombarded the
same uh so that's why undergarment would not
uh so that's why undergarment would not
be able to live well you had anagram his
living house for life but in Ireland
would not be able to live a house for
life because simply why why would he bear
because simply why why would he bear
annoyance and harassment of the senses
that have no desire towards those things
so it's just discomfort basically it's
factually uncomfortable
Central perceptions fancy but when
undeveloped mind meets Central
perceptions feels their discomfort knows
no other escape from it other than going
towards the pleasure that that
discomfort offers in return and that's
it you took debate
it's exactly the bed
so that's the progress not going in the
direction of debate regardless of the
discomfort um and uh and then uh yeah sometimes you
um and uh and then uh yeah sometimes you
would just have to avoid this conflict
if it's too much pressure it's it's
better to upgrade the environment where
you won't be as pressured but yeah then
don't confuse that for Progress yeah yes
you still recognize that well but have I
seen the burial the danger and you know
vomited the kind of the desire out and
so on or or am I just sheltered here
and that's something if you're
transparent you know the answer without
having to go back to the environment
they will provoke you
so the bait is the pressure
well debate is the pleasure that you get
if you give in to the pressure
the bait is hidden in the pleasure let's
say like that
so acting out towards it means
biting taking taking on the bed it's the
gratification the danger and it also
could be the Escape when you understand
it
yeah it's like putting honey on a razor
blade yeah and then making it
well the poison is a drink
that's the
the subtlety of sensuality is the
it's the subtlety of debate you don't
really see it your senses do not
perceive your eyes ears they don't see
anything that's disagreeable and so on
but the mind is factually pressured by
it and if you on that level you discern
debate then you know that there is a poison in
then you know that there is a poison in
a drink that is otherwise undetectable
by your senses but now the knowledge
that it is poisonous
that that cannot change
so although you can't smell it you can't
smell the poison you can't touch it
you can't see it but you can know that
it's there
and when you know that it's there no
amount of pressure will make you take
that drink
when you fully discern that it is there
actually you see it on that mental level
because as we said before if you weren't
why why does sensuality need to pressure you
why does sensuality need to pressure you
towards acting if it's wholesome if it's
good why does it need to bombard you and
why does it need to bombard you and
trick you and manipulate you and control
you why does he have a nature of a trap
why do you know like if it's if it's
generally good why is it set up in a way
that I end up being trapped
and that's their whole points like you
really you could recognize the pattern
and you see yeah so this I don't know
the implications of this setup but I
know that it cannot be for my welfare
as the students would say he knows it
like a hunter does not set up a trap for
a welfare of the deer
so the mark reflects that anything that
has a nature of a trap Hey look
cannot be for my welfare I don't know
who set it up I don't know why and I
don't need to know all I know is how to
Raccoon is a trap when I see it and not
fall into it kind of
diff no it's one just
uh and I think you should try to
convince people about it
you're devaluing the actual practice
if somebody needs convincing they're not
going to make the effort necessary for
understanding you need to meet the instruction halfway
you need to meet the instruction halfway
if it's shut down your throat and put on
you it's not it's going to be seen as
something completely different from what
it actually is I mean it's not obvious
for everybody that sensuality is a
danger no no of course not
well if it were obvious we wouldn't need
all the instruction to free yourself
from it